Cristiano Cantore

Sapienza Università di Roma Dipartimento di Economia e Diritto Via del Castro Laurenziano, 9 6sto Piano Ala B 00161 Roma

E-mail: cristiano.cantore@uniroma1.it Web: http://www.cristianocantore.com

FIELDS OF Interest

Business Cycle Theory, Monetary and Fiscal Policy, Applied Macroeconomics

Current EMPLOYMENT **Professor of Economics**, Sapienza University of Rome. from 03/2023

OTHER Affiliations Fellow at the Centre for Macroeconomics (LSE), the Rimini Centre for Economic Anal-

ysis and Centre for International Macroeconomics (Surrey).

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Economics University of Kent, (passed without corrections). 2011

Dissertation Examiners: Prof. M. Ellison (Oxford), Dr. K.Shibayama (Kent).

M.Sc. in Economics, Pompeu Fabra University, Barcelona. 2005 2004

B.A. in Economics and Statistics, L. Bocconi University, Milan.

Previous Positions Guest Lecturer, London School of Economics, London. 01/2022 to 07/2022

Bank of England Pole Director at the Centre for Macroeconomics (LSE). 02/2021

to 02/2023

Research Advisor, Research Hub, Bank of England. 07/2021 to 02/2023

Reader in Economics (Part-Time), University of Surrey, Guildford. 08/2018 to

02/2023

09/2018 to 06/2021 Senior Research Economist, Research Hub, Bank of England.

Senior Lecturer in Economics, University of Surrey, Guildford. 04/2013 to 07/2018 10/2021 to 10/2021Visiting Professor, Collegio Carlo Alberto, Turin.

Visiting Professor, University of California San Diego. 02/2014 to 07/2014

Visiting Research Fellow, Banco de España, Madrid. 04/2012 to 08/2012

Lecturer in Economics, University of Surrey, Guildford. 09/2009 to 03/2013

Visiting Professor, University of Cagliari. 01/2012 to 02/2012

Intern, European Central Bank, Economics DG. 08/2008 to 10/2008

Intern, OECD, Economic Department, Country desk 1. 07/2007 to 09/2007

PUBLICATIONS

(2024) Unwinding quantitative easing: State dependency and household heterogeneity,

joint with Pascal Meichtry (Banque de France). European Economic Review, 170,

104865.

(2021) Workers, Capitalists, and the Government: Fiscal Policy and Income (Re)Distribution,

joint with Lukas Freund (University of Cambridge). Journal of Monetary Economics,

119, 58-74.

(2020) The Missing Link: Labor Share and Monetary Policy, joint with Filippo Ferroni (Chicago FED) and Miguel León-Ledesma (University of Kent). Journal of the European Economic Association, 19(3), 1592–1620.

(2019) Optimal Fiscal and Monetary Policy, Debt Crisis and Management, joint with Paul Levine (University of Surrey), Giovanni Melina (IMF) and Joseph Pearlman (City University London). Macroeconomic Dynamics, 23-3, 1166-1204.

(2017) The Dynamics of hours worked and technology, joint with Filippo Ferroni (Chicago FED) and Miguel León-Ledesma (University of Kent). Journal of Economic Dynamics and Control, 82, 67-82.

(2015) CES technology and Business Cycle fluctuations, joint with Paul Levine (University of Surrey), Joseph Pearlman (City University London) and Bo Yang (Swansea University). Journal of Economic Dynamics and Control, 61(C), 133-151.

(2014) Shocking Stuff: Technology, Hours and Factor Substitution, joint with Miguel León-Ledesma (University of Kent), Peter McAdam (ECB) and Alpo Willman (ECB). Journal of the European Economic Association, 12-1, 108-128

(2014) A Fiscal Stimulus and Jobless Recovery, joint with Paul Levine (University of Surrey) and Giovanni Melina (IMF). Scandinavian Journal of Economics, 116-3, 669-701

(2012) Getting Normalization Right: Dealing with 'Dimensional Constants' in Macroeconomics, joint with Paul Levine (University of Surrey). Journal of Economic Dynamics and Control, 36, 1931-1949

(2012) A Fiscal Stimulus with Deep Habits and Optimal Monetary Policy, joint with Paul Levine (University of Surrey), Giovanni Melina (IMF) and Bo Yang (Swansea University). Economics Letters, 117-1, 348-353

BOOK CHAPTERS

(2013) The Science and Art of DSGE Modelling I. Construction and Bayesian Estimation, joint with V. Gabriel, P. Levine, J. Pearlman and B. Yang. in 'Handbook of Research Methods and Applications in Empirical Macroeconomics', eds N. Hashimzade and M. Thornton, Edward Elgar Publishing

(2013) The Science and Art of DSGE Modelling II. Model Comparisons, Model Validation, Policy Analysis and General Discussion, joint with V. Gabriel, P. Levine, J. Pearlman and B. Yang. in 'Handbook of Research Methods and Applications in Empirical Macroeconomics', eds N. Hashimzade and M. Thornton, Edward Elgar Publishing

RELEVANT EXPERIENCE

Teaching

- Sapienza University of Roma (2023 to date):
 - *Undergraduate*: Politica Economica.
 - Masters: Economic Policy, Teorie e Politiche Macroeconomiche.

- Monetary Economics and Aggregate Fluctuations, *Master in Economics* London School of Economics, London.

 Jan-Apr. 2022
- Introduction to Dynamic Macroeconomics, *Master in Economics*, **Collegio Carlo Alberto**, Turin. 5-15/10/2021
- University of Surrey (2009 to 2022):
 - Undergraduate: Intermediate Macroeconomics Theory and Applications; International Economics and Finance; Economic Data Analysis.
 - Masters: Macroeconomics; International Trade; Advanced Economic Theory.
 - PhD: Advanced Macroeconomics I; Topics in Empirical Macroeconomics.

Training courses on DSGE models

CIMS Summer School, University of Surrey.	10/09/2024
Central Bank of Paraguay, Online.	15-26/03 & 3-4/04/2024
CIMS Summer School, University of Surrey.	11-15/09/2023
CIMS Summer School, University of Surrey.	12-16/09/2022
CIMS Summer School, University of Surrey.	7 - 14/09/2021
CIMS Summer School, University of Surrey.	7-11/09/2020
CIMS Summer School, University of Surrey.	9-13/09/2019
CIMS Summer School, University of Surrey.	3-7/09/2018
CIMS Summer School, University of Surrey.	4-8/09/2017
DIW, Berlin.	25-26/07/2017
CIMS Summer School, University of Surrey.	30/8-3/9/2016
Central Bank of Nigeria, Abuja.	6-10/06/2016
Central Bank of Nigeria, Abuja.	25 - 29/01/2016
CIMS Summer School, University of Surrey.	7-11/09/2015
Computational Economics Summer School, University of Caglia	ri. 6-9/07/2015
CIMS Easter School, University of Surrey.	20-22 April 2015
CIMS Summer School, University of Surrey.	8-13/09/2014
CIMS Summer School, University of Surrey.	9-13/09/2013
RES Easter School, University of Birmingham.	14-18/04/2013
CIMS Summer School, University of Surrey.	10-14/09/2012
PhD program, University of Porto, Portugal.	30/1-2/2/2012
Scottish PhD program, University of Glasgow, Scotland.	5-6/7/2011
National Institute of Public Policy and Finance, New Delhi, Inc.	, ,

Administration Duties

Member of the Senate, University of Surrey.	2017-2018	
Job market committee (committee chair in 2015), University of Surrey.	2012-2018	
Deputy Head of School, University of Surrey.	2015	
PhD admission director, University of Surrey.	2014-2018	
Undergraduate admission officer; Departmental seminars organizer. University of Surrey.		
2009-2013		

GRANTS,
AWARDS
EDITORIAL
ACTIVITIES AND
COMMITTEES

• Organized 4th Sailing the Macro Workshop, Ortygia.

2024.

• ESRC Peer Review College member.

2023 to date

• Organized 3rd Sailing the Macro Workshop, Ortygia.	2023.
• Scientific committee of the MMF annual conference.	2023 to date.
• Money, Macro and Finance Society committee member.	2023 to 2024
• Editor of the Bank of England Staff Working Papers.	2018 to 2023
• Organized 9th Annual MMF PhD Conference.	21/23-04-2022
• Organized First Annual BEAR Conference: The Monetary Toolkit.	25/26-02-2022

- Organized workshop on *Productivity and Structural Change* sponsored by NIESR, The productivity institute, MMF and the Bank of England.
 26-11-2021
- Organized the *Macroeconomic Consequences of Technological Change workshop* sponsored by MMF, University of Kent and the Bank of England. 10/11-6-2021
- Organized conference *Income Distribution*, *Wealth Distribution and Central Bank Policies* sponsored by CFM, LSE and the Bank of England. 28-2-2020
- Scientific committee Money, Macroeconomics and Finance PhD conference. 2018
- European Commission / Type of funding scheme: CO-CREATION-08-2016/2017: Modelling and evaluating the socio-economic impacts of research and innovation with the suite of macro- and regional-economic models. 323,440€ at fEC as coinvestigator. 2017-2018
- Scientific committee Spanish Economic Association Simposio. 2013-2015
- RES Special Project Grant funding the 2nd Workshop on Structural Change & Macroeconomic Dynamics. 2,600£ 2012
- Banco de España Fellowship 'Trabajos de investigación sobre economía'. 2012
- ESRC grant: Monetary and Fiscal Policy Rules with Labour Market and Financial Frictions. 347,000£ at fEC as co-investigator. 2010-2012
- ESRC PhD scholarship, University of Kent. 2006-2009
- Postgraduate scholarship, Carlos III University. 2005-2006

Conferences and Presentations **2024:** Banco Central de Colombia, (Online); 3rd Dynare Workshop for Advanced Users, JRC Ispra; ICMAIF 2024, University of Crete; Padova Macro Talks 2024, University of Padua; Paris School of Economics; EIEF (Rome); European Commission, DG ECFIN (Online); Society of Nonlinear Dynamics and Econometrics, University of Padova.

2023: ASSA Meetings 2023, New Orleans; University of York; Bank of England; Norges Bank; FinPro3, Bank of Italy; EEA-ESEM23, Universitat Pompeu Fabra, Workshop on Macroeconomics and Survey Data, National Bank of Belgium.

2022: Theories and Methods in Macroeconomics 2022, Kings College London; Royal Economic Society (invited for policy discussion), University of Reading; Banca d'Italia; Society for Nonlinear Dynamics and Econometrics 2022, Online; Universitat Autonoma de Barcelona; Barcelona Summer Forum: Monetary Policy and Central Banking, Universitat Autonoma de Barcelona; Salento Macro Meetings, Lecce; Università La Sapienza, Roma; Université catholique de Louvain; Household Heterogeneity conference, Banque de France; 4th European Midwest Micro/Macro Conference (EM3C), Frankfurt School of Finance and Management.

2021: 11th ifo Conference on Macroeconomics and Survey Data, Ifo Institute; University of Surrey; CFM workshop, LSE; 3TM, Banque de France; 8th Bank of Italy-CEPR Conference on Money, Banking and Finance: "Closing the Gaps: The Future of Stabilisation Policies after the COVID-19 Pandemic", Bank of Italy; EEA/ESEM 2021; 52nd MMF

Annual conference; 1st Sailing the Macro Workshop, Ventotene; Collegio Carlo Alberto, Turin; Macroeconometric Workshop, King's College London; Universidad de Antioquia, Medellín; Workshop on Empirical Monetary Economics 2021, SciencePo, Paris; European Winter Meeting of the Econometric Society 2021, UB, Barcelona.

2020: Birkbeck, University of London; EEA/ESEM 2020, University of Rotterdam; 2020 Central Bank Macro Modelling Workshop, Norges Bank; XXV meeting of the Central Bank Researchers Network (CEMLA), Banco Central del Uruguay.

2019: Banca d'Italia; 7th Belgian Macroeonomic Wokshop (invited lecture), University of Ghent; EEA/ESEM 2019, University of Manchester; 3rd Workshop on 'Macroeconomic and Financial Time Series Analysis', University of Lancaster; CEPR Network on Macroeconomic Modelling and Model Comparison, Goethe University Frankfurt; 2019 Royal Economic Society Annual Conference, University of Warwick; International Monetary Fund, Washington DC; 27th Annual Symposium of the Society for Nonlinear Dynamics and Econometrics, Dallas FED. 'Labor Income Share Developments: Drivers and Policy Implications', Bank of Greece, Athens.

2018: Ridge Forum December 2018: Macroeconomics and Development, Buenos Aires; 6th Workshop in Macro Banking and Finance, Alghero; 71st European Meeting of the Econometric Society, Cologne; Bank of England; 14th Dynare Conference, European Central Bank; Deutsche Bundesbank, Frankfurt; Universität de Barcelona; Université de Lorraine, Nancy.

2017: 16th workshop "Macronomic Dynamics: theory and applications", Università Cattolica de Sacro Cuore Milano; XI Workshop on Public Design: "Structural Changes, Labor Markets and Policy", Universitat de Girona; Bank of Japan, Tokyo; 13th Dynare Conference, University of Tokyo; Università di Verona; DIW, Berlin; 1st Research Conference of the CEPR Network on Macroeconomic Modelling and Model Comparison MMCN, Goethe University Frankfurt; Bank of England, London; International Monetary Fund, Washington DC; Federal Reserve Bank, Chicago; Collegio Carlo Alberto, Turin; University of Surrey; University of Kent.

2016: University of Portsmouth; Workshop 'Developments in Macroeconomics' Università of Rome La Sapienza; Lacea-Lames, Eafit, Medellin; Spanish Economic Association Simposio, Bilbao.

2015: University of Glasgow, Business School; Mid-West Macro Meeting, University of Washington St. Louis; University of Manchester; Lacea meeting, Santa Cruz, Bolivia; Spanish Economic Association Simposio, Girona.

2014: Rice University, Huston (TX); University of California San Diego; 10^{th} Dynare conference, Banque de France, Paris; Lacea Lames meeting, Sao Paulo; Spanish Economic Association Simposio, Palma de Mallorca.

2013: Spanish Economic Association Simposio, Santander; Xi'an Jiaotong-Liverpool University, SuZhou China; 9th Dynare conference, SUFE Shanghai; MBF Workshop, Universita' di Milano Bicocca; Reserve Bank of New Zealand; Universita' di Pavia; Utrecht School of Economics; Universita' di Padova; Workshop on Empirical Macroeconomics, University of Ghent.

2012: Spanish Economic Association Simposio, Vigo; Cardiff Business School; SIE, Matera; 8th Dynare Conference, Zurich; CIMS Conference, Guildford; EEA-ESEM University of Malaga; Structural Change and Macroeconomic Dynamics University of Cagliari; University of Porto; Banco de España; Workshop on Structural Change & Macroeconomic Dynamics, University of Cagliari.

2011: NIPFP, New Delhi; Structural Change and Macroeconomic Performance workshop at University of Cagliari.

2010: MONFISPOL Conference, London Metropolitan University, London; Computa-

tional Economics and Finance 2010 Conference, Department of Economics, City University, London; Spanish Economic Association Simposio, Department of Economics, Universidad Autonoma de Madrid.

2009: Spanish Economic Association Simposio, Department of Economics, University of Valencia; Association of Southern European Economist Annual conference, Department of Economics, Boğaziçi University, Istanbul; 41st Annual Conference, Money Macro and Finance research group, Bradford School of Management, Bradford University; Annual international conference on macroeconomic analysis and international finance, Department of Economics, University of Crete, Rethymno; Department of Financial Economics, University of Hannover; Department of Economics, University of Konstanz.

2008: Macroeconomic and Financial Linkages: Theory and Practice. Peterhouse College, University of Cambridge; Association of Southern European Economic Theorists (ASSET) 2008 meeting. EUI, Florence; Doctoral Workshop on Dynamic Macroeconomics, Universite Louis Pasteur Strasbourg; Southern Workshop in Macroeconomics, University of Auckland and Reserve Bank of New Zealand.

2007: Second Doctoral Workshop, EBIM, University of Bielefeld.

REFEREEING EXPERIENCE

Journal of Political Economy; Quarterly Journal of Economics; The Review of Economic Studies; American Economic Review: Insights; Journal of Monetary Economics; Journal of Economic Theory; Journal of the European Economic Association; The Economic Journal; Review of Economics and Statistics; Review of Economic Dynamics; Journal of Applied Econometrics; International Economic Review; Journal of Economic Dynamics and Control; Journal of Money Credit and Banking; European Economic Review; Macroeconomic Dynamics; Oxford Bulletin of Economics and Statistics; The Scandinavian Journal of Economics; Economic Inquiry; Economic Letters; Oxford Economic papers; BE Journal of Macroeconomics; Journal of Macroeconomics; Economica; SERIEs; Economic Modelling; Southern Economic Journal; Scottish Journal of Political Economy; Bank of England Staff working papers; Deutsche Bundesbank Discussion Paper Series; Czech National Bank Working Papers; ESRC-UKRI; ANVUR (Italian Research Evaluation); PRIN (Italian Minsitry of Education research grants); Research Grants Council Hong Kong.

PHD SUPERVISION AND PHD EXAMINATIONS

- PhD Student Supervised: Vedanta Dhamija (Surrey, 2023) Joseph Grilli (Surrey, 2019); Tae Min Lee (Surrey, 2017); Marcelo Almeida (Surrey, 2017); Matteo Ghilardi (Surrey, 2013).
- PhD viva committee: Giuliano de Queiroz Ferreira (São Paulo, 2023) Silvio Tunis (Cagliari, 2023); Alessandro Cantelmo (London City, 2018); Fred Iklaga (Surrey, 2017); Diana Lima (Surrey, 2017); Jonathan Swarbrick (Surrey, 2016); Veronica Arcurio Vasconez (Paris 1, 2015).

Computer Skills

Matlab, Stata, FORTRAN95, Python, Maple, Mathematica, LATEX

Memberships

Royal economic society; American economic association; European economic association; Spanish economic association, Latin American economic association.

LANGUAGES

Italian (Native), English (Fluent), Spanish (Fluent).

CITIZENSHIPS Italian, British

updated: November 2024